Guide to the Paris Cleveland Gardner Papers, 1834-1976 RL.00434
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Paris Cleveland Gardner papers
1834-1976
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gardner, Paris Cleveland, 1887-1974
RL.00434
5.4 Linear Feet
3,156 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The papers of Paris Cleveland Gardner, lawyer and politician of Cleveland County, N.C., and Washington, D.C., were acquired by the Rubenstein Library through gift in 1975.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1887 Jan. 7 Born, Shelby, Cleveland County, N.C.
1916 LL.B., University of North Carolina.
1916-1924 Practiced law in Hominy, Osage County, OK
1919 Married Tazewell Lloyd of Chapel Hill, N.C.
1924-1939 Practiced law in Shelby, N.C.
1926-1932 Solicitor of Recorder's Court, Cleveland County, N.C.
1939 Relocated to Chapel Hill, N.C.
1941-1962 Staff attorney, Federal Trade Commission, Washington, D.C.
1974 Sept. 16 Died, Chapel Hill, N.C.
Collection Overview
The papers of Paris Cleveland Gardner span the years 1834 to 1976, though they fall chiefly in the period 1920 to 1951. They consist of correspondence, legal papers, case files, printed matter, and clippings.
Included are some papers relating to Gardner's personal life and affairs in Cleveland County, N.C., and in Oklahoma. Of particular interest is correspondence relating to local, state, and national Democratic Party politics and elections in North Carolina in the 1920s and 1930s. Correspondents of note in this group include Richard Fountain, O. Max Gardner, and Robert R. Reynolds. Also present are some case files relating to Gardner's private legal practice, including the 1917 case of Leroy Cowthen, a member of the International Workers of the World (I.W.W.) who was being harassed; the investigation of the Humphreys family claims to the title of a profitable oil field near Beaumont, Tex.; and a file on the Shelby (N.C.) Building and Loan Association. Also included in a file of miscellaneous material is some genealogical material on the Harman family.
By far the bulk of the papers are represented by the Federal Trade Commission files. As an attorney-examiner with the F.T.C. between 1941 and 1962, Gardner worked with cases involving alleged deceptive advertising practices in the print media and radio. The individual files contain factual summaries of evidence in each case as well as occasional recommendations for action.
While the files here probably do not represent a complete record of Gardner's work with the F.T.C., they do provide ample illustration of the methods and practices of the government as it attempted to regulate false and misleading advertising.
Most of the cases represented in these files went through the office of Gardner's superior, D. B. Gatling, who was Chief of the Division of Radio and Periodical Advertising. The F.T.C. files in the so-called Packets and Alphabetical Files contain documentation regarding routine complaints about mostly small proprietary companies, though there are exceptions - most notably, the series of files on the American Tobacco Company, relating principally to misuse and distortions of testimonials from tobacco buyers and smokers in advertising. For the most part, the cases in these files rarely went beyond the preliminary stages of investigation. The Secondary Review Files are generally more substantive, representing cases on which some sort of action was taken. Also included are some of Gardner's personnel files from the F.T.C. While the reason for their inclusion with the case files is not altogether clear, the original order and contents of these files has been maintained nevertheless.
Advertising -- Tobacco trade; Lawyers -- North Carolina; Deceptive advertising; Cleveland County (N.C.) -- Politics and government; United States. Federal Trade Commission; Reynolds, Robert Rice, 1884-1963; Humphrey family; Industrial Workers of the World; Gardner, Paris Cleveland, 1887-1974; Gardner, Paris Cleveland, 1887-1974; Fountain, Richard Tillman, 1885-1945; Gardner, Oliver Max, 1882-1947; American Tobacco Company; Democratic Party (N.C.)
- Information Folder
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains biographical information on Gardner and his family; material on the structure and operations of the F.T.C.
- Correspondence Series
  Principally personal correspondence relating to real estate interests in Oklahoma and politics in North Carolina and Cleveland County. Arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1919-1943 and undated, 4 folders (Box 1)
- Legal Papers Series
  Includes correspondence, legal papers, clippings, and other papers relating to legal cases with which Gardner was involved. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Leroy Cowthen case, 1917 (Box 1)
  - Crowell vs. Crowell, 1920-1924 and undated (Box 1)
  - Humphreys family case, 1834-1932 (Box 1)
  - Shelby and Cleveland County Building and Loan Association, M. A. Gardner residence, 1928-1929 (Box 1)
  - Legal papers, 1926-1931 and undated (Box 1)
- Printed Materials Series
  Includes campaign brochures, broadsides, flyers, advertisements, sample ballots, printed speeches, etc., almost all from North Carolina.
  - Printed materials, 1918-1935 and undated (Box 1)
- Miscellany Series
  Includes Cleveland County, N.C., political lists, Harman family genealogical material, and other materials.
  - Miscellany, 1926-1948 and undated (Box 1)
- Clippings Series
  - Clippings, 1918-1936 and undated, 3 folders (Box 2)
- F.T.C. Files Series
  Arrangement note
  Includes subseries: Packets, 1-13; Alpha Files, A-W; and Secondary Review Cases, 1948-1951.
  - Packets Subseries
    - Packet 1: Active Clothing Co.; Allegany Oil Co.; American Cigarette and Cigar Co.; Aurex Corporation; B. T. Babbit, Inc. (Box 2)
    - Packet 1: Burbrooke Mfg. Co. et al.; Buschs; Colony House (Box 2)
    - Packet 1: Cosmetic industry (Box 2)
    - Packet 2: Capital City College, Inc., et al.; Cello-Plastic Chemical Co.; Ceres Lunch, Inc. (Box 3)
    - Packet 2: M.A. Chapman & Son; Chaston; Cigarette Investigation (Box 3)
    - Packet 2: Clean-Rite Vacuum Stores (Box 3)
    - Packet 2: Clopay Corporation; Louis Cohen, et al.; Colorcrete Industries, Inc.; Colorthru Chemical; Combustion Service, Inc. (Box 3)
    - Packet 2: Combustion Service Co.; Comfort Manufacturing Co.; OOFC Retail Liquor Dealers Assoc. (Box 3)
    - Packet 2: Electrovox Company; Elmira Steel Co.; Emerson Drug Co. (Box 3)
    - Packet 3: H.D. Fine, et al.; F.W. Fitch Co.; Forty Second Street Photo Shop; Francis Keil & Son, Inc.; Freilay & Sons, Inc. (Box 4)
    - Packet 3: General Electric Co.; General Motors; Globe Laboratories; Louis Goldberg (ACME Mail Order Houses); Good Value Bargain House (Box 4)
    - Packet 3: Goulard & Clean, Inc.; Gulf & West Indies Co., Inc.; Earl Hall (United Watch Co.); Harding Glass Company (Box 4)
    - Packet 3: Hercules Liquor Products Corp., N.Y.; C.L. Hoffman Corp.; Home Service Co., et al. (Box 4)
    - Packet 3: Hoover Manufacturing & Sales Co. (Box 4)
    - Packet 3: H. G. Hornbrook (Apex Oil Product Co.); C. Howard Hunt Pen Co.; J.M. Hughes (Box 4)
    - Packet 4: International Research; Interstate Home Equipment Co., Inc.; Jackson Research Labs (Box 5)
    - Packet 4: David Jacobs & Allied News-Photo Service Corp.; B. Jadow Inc.; Kaplan & Lacoff; Katz Drug Co.; Harry Kaufman, Inc. (Box 5)
    - Packet 4: Milton S., Kronheim & Son, Inc., et al. (second investigation); Kruset (Box 5)
    - Packet 4: The Kenyon Studies; Koh-I-Noor Pencil Co., et al. (Box 5)
    - Packet 4: Kopy Kat; The Korby Co. (Box 5)
    - Packet 4: Lane Drug Co.; Lee Products Co.; Lekas & Drivas; Long's (Box 5)
    - Packet 4: Lion Oil Refining Co.; London Handkerchief Co.; Londonderry, Inc.; MacMillan Petroleum Corp.; R. H. Macy & Co.; Majestic Metal Novelty Co. (Box 5)
    - Packet 5: Marco Company, Inc. (Box 6)
    - Packet 5: Mira-Glo Products, Inc. (Box 6)
    - Packet 5: Merck & Co., Inc.; Nylo Company, Inc.; O'Cedar Corp. (Box 6)
    - Packet 5: Penn Poultry Service (Box 6)
    - Packet 5: Perfect Brush Manufacturing Co.; Peter Morton Sportsware, Inc.; Printwell Co., et al.; C.W. Products Co.; Rex Remedy Co.; Rice Sticks Dry Goods Co.; A. Rabin; Ruckel Manufacturing Co. (Box 6)
    - Packet 6: P.C. Gardner Medical Claim (Box 6)
    - Packet 7: American Tobacco Co. (Box 7)
    - Packet 8: Gardner, P. C. - Official Efficiency Rating; Application for Leave; Efficiency Rating; New and old forms of contact letters (Box 7)
    - Packet 8: Secondary Reviews, 1949 July-1950 Mar. See also 12, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Packet 8: American Tobacco Co., 1 (Box 8)
    - Packet 9: American Tobacco Co., 2, interviews of witnesses (Box 8)
    - Packet 10: American Tobacco Co., 3 (Box 8)
    - Packet 10: American Tobacco Co., 4 (Box 8)
    - Packet 11: Parr Vitamin Co., et al.; Pioneer Publications, Inc.; Sea Island Mills, Inc.; The Sealtex Co.; Searta Associates, Inc., et al. (Box 8)
    - Packet 11: Siegel Rothschild Gans Brothers, Inc.; The Silex Co.; Somerville Mfg. Co.; Southern Chemical Co.; Joseph Sperling (Box 8)
    - Packet 11: Steelco Stainless Steel Co., Inc.; Stone-Tarlow Co., Inc.; Students Book Co.; E.Z. Suds Products Co. (Box 8)
    - Packet 11: The Sullivan Co.; Thomas B. Keen Co., et al.; Tomlinson of Highpoint (Box 8)
    - Packet 12: R.M. Taylor Co.; Turbanwav, Inc.; William C. Tyson (Box 9)
    - Packet 13: Unnamed automobile dealers, 1:1 (Box 9)
    - Packet 13: Unnamed automobile dealers, 1:2 (Box 9)
    - Packet 13: Unnamed Tobacco Manufacturers; United States Shoe Corp.; U.S. Surplus Commodities Co., Inc.; Vanleigh Furniture Co., Inc.; Vit-O-Cel Dietaids Co., et al. (Box 9)
    - Packet 13: Waldmere Hatcher,et al.; Walsh Refractories, Corp.; Washington Tobacco Co.; Western Electric Co., Inc.; Williams Gold Refining Co., Inc.; Willys-Overland Motors, Inc., et al.; Zenith Radio Corp. (Box 9)
  - Alphabetical Files Subseries
    - A-B: (Box 10)
      - The American Polish Co. (Box 10)
      - American Tobacco Co. (memo) (Box 10)
      - Beaverton Bulbs (Box 10)
      - Bristol-Meyers Co. (Box 10)
      - Builders Products (Easter Small) trading as Builders Products (Box 10)
      - Burton Sales Co. (Box 10)
    - C:
      - Chattanooga Medicine Co. (Box 10)
      - Certa-Vin Co. (Box 10)
      - Chicago Roller Skate Co. (Box 10)
      - Consumer Credit vs. P.C. Gardner (Box 10)
      - Courant Distributing Co. (Box 10)
    - D-F:
      - Dandruff Corp. (Box 10)
      - Enterprise Paint (Box 10)
      - Florence Etta's Wyo-Min-Pro, Inc. (Box 10)
      - Foley & Co. (Box 10)
      - Franksville Specialty Co. (Box 10)
    - G-H:
      - Garlick-y Laboratories (Box 10)
      - Gates Rubber Co. (Box 10)
      - Gum Laboratories, Inc. (Box 10)
      - H-A-P-I-A Distributors (Box 10)
      - House of Marshall (Box 10)
      - Hydro Power Sales, Inc. (Box 10)
    - J-L:
      - Janney-Semple Hill & Co. (Box 10)
      - Jewel Promotions (Box 10)
      - Kelife Products, Inc. (Box 10)
      - Knomark Manufacturing Co. (Box 10)
      - Dr. Larson's Calf-Nipple Feeder (Box 10)
    - M:
      - Marcellus Co. (Box 10)
      - Mils, Inc. (Box 10)
      - Milter Products (Box 10)
      - Miner's Medicine Co., et al. (Box 10)
      - Miss Ruth, Inc. (Box 10)
      - Mogelewsky (Box 10)
    - N: (Box 11)
      - New Book Company (Box 11)
      - New York Tailors (Box 11)
    - O-Sc:
      - Oregon Drug Products (Box 11)
      - Perma Plastic Products (Box 11)
      - Pierce & Stevens, Inc. (Box 11)
      - Premier Knitting Co., et al. (Box 11)
      - Rest-Well Bed Board Co. (Box 11)
      - Ansel W. Robison Co. (Box 11)
      - Scientific Electric Co. (Box 11)
      - Scotch Woolen Mills (Box 11)
      - I Schwartz (Box 11)
    - Sea:
      - Sears, Roebuck & Co. (Box 11)
    - Sem-Sw:
      - R.B. Sealer, Inc. (Box 11)
      - Shemano's Hair & Scalp Method, Inc. (Box 11)
      - Slack Filled Griffin Smtih (Box 11)
      - Sonotone Corp. (Box 11)
      - Standard Chemical Mfg. Co. (Box 11)
      - Standard Dry Wall Products, Inc. (Box 11)
      - H.A. Stuart Co.; H. Swartz; Sweet Brier, Inc. (Box 11)
    - T-V:
      - Talbo, Inc. (Box 11)
      - Tecots Products Co., Inc. (Box 11)
      - The Texas Co. (Box 11)
      - Theobald Industries (Box 11)
      - Tower Eye Glass Co. (Box 11)
      - Townsend National Weekly, Inc. (Box 11)
      - Joseph Triner Corp. (Box 11)
      - Van Patton Pharmaceutical Co. (Box 11)
      - Viewtone Television and Radio Corp. (Box 11)
    - W:
      - W & M Products Co. (Box 11)
      - Whitehall Pharmacal Co. (Box 11)
      - Wildroot Company, Inc. (Box 11)
  - Secondary Reviews Subseries
    - Secondary Reviews 1948 Jan.-1950 July See also packet 8 for 1950 Mar., 8 Folders (Box 12)
    - Secondary Reviews 1950 Aug.-1951 Aug., 7 folders (Box 13)
    - Miscellany: Worksheets for 1948-1951, Division of Radio and Periodical Advertising; Index of Active cases, 1949 Feb. (Box 13)
    - Miscellany: Independent Tobacco Experts Survey, 1941. (Box 13)